Festival Accompanying Chapter
Part Five
The Final Piece
saa, wasuremashou sono mirai ga
Come, let us forget about the future...
Planning
Takeshi Oikawa
Akihiro Kawamura
Akihiro Yuasa
Original Work ・ Original Story/Supervision
Ryukishi07/07th Expansion
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni"
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai"
mata chinurarete yuku nante
...ending up stained in blood again.
Series Composition
Toshifumi Kawase
Character Design
Overall Animation Supervisor
Kyuuta Sakai
Art Director
Chikako Shibata
Color Design
Shinji Matsumoto
namanurui kaze toguro wo maitara
If the soft wind coils up...
Camera Director
Masayuki Kawaguchi
Editing
Masahiro Matsumura
Music
Kenji Kawai
Sound Director
Hozumi Gouda
sore ga tabun aizu
...that is probably a sign.
nukedashitette
Break free.
Opening Theme
"Naraku no Hana"
(Flower in Hell)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition
Arrangement
Eiko Shimamiya
Tomoyuki Nakazawa
Takeshi Ozaki
kanashisugiru unmei kara
From your heart-wrenching fate.
Music Producer
Music Production
Akira Yoshikawa
Frontier Works
anata wa naraku no hana ja nai
You are not a flower in hell.
Producers
Mika Nomura
Hiroyuki Oomori
Takeshi Okamura
sonna basho de sakanaide
Don't blossom in such a place.
Animation Producer
Animation Production
Kouji Iijima
Studio Deen
sakanaide
Don't blossom there.
karametorarete ikanaide
Don't get entangled.
oto mo naku tobikau toki no kakera
Fragments of time flutter about without a sound.
Kai
Hi
ni
ra
ku
Koro
gu
no
shi
Na
Kai
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
Director
Chiaki Kon
These are someone's words...
（梨花(りか)）誰かが言ってた
“運命は自分で切り開くものだ”と
"Fate is something you can carve yourself."
[Hinamizawa Lot-for-sale Tour]
But to be given such an opportunity...
でも そのきっかけを
与えてくれるのは―
...might take a small miracle.
ほんの小さな
奇跡なのかもしれない
[Tag: Lot-for-sale Tour Participant, Mr. Ichirou Maebara]
（伊知郎(いちろう)）ハア
（子供たち）わあ 逃げろ！
ああ 待って待って待って
待って ああ！
（悟史(さとし)）ありがとう 魅音(みおん)
Thanks, Mion.
（魅音）えっ？　ああ 何が？
For what?
For always being so attentive to Satoko.
（悟史）沙都子(さとこ)に
いつも気を使ってくれて―
Thanks.
ありがとう
沙都子は 学校にいる間は―
While Satoko is at school...
本当に少しだけ
肩の力を抜けるみたいなんだ
...she seems to be able to relax for a little bit.
I'm sure this is a very peaceful time for her.
それは きっと沙都子にとって
とても優しい時間になってる
おじさんは 感謝されることなんか
何もしてないよ
I have done nothing worth being thankful for.
（悟史）そんなことない
（魅音）えっ？
That's not true.
That's absolutely not true.
（悟史）そんなこと… ない
Please help her.
（悟史）助けてほしいんだ
（魅音）えっ？
僕１人の力じゃ
沙都子に笑顔は戻せない
I can't bring back Satoko's smile by myself.
I need the help of a strong-willed person such as you.
魅音みたいな力強い人の
助けが要るんだよ
But I'm Mion of the Sonozaki family.
でも あたし園崎(そのざき)家の魅音だよ？
Satoko will probably think of me as a nuisance...
沙都子は
あたしのこと迷惑に思わないかな？
I'm here as well.
僕も一緒にいるから
Then...
じゃあさ 今日 学校が終わったら
沙都子を遊びに誘ってみる？
Wanna invite Satoko to play after school is over?
家に帰ると
叔母さんにいろいろ言われて―
She'll be berated by Aunt again once she returns home...
表に出られなくなってしまう
かもしれない
...and she might not be allowed to go outside anymore.
Then how about this?
ならさ あれだ
What if you told her she joined a club?
“部活動に加わった”って
言うのはどう？
A club?
部活？
うん　部活ってことにして
学校で遊んでから帰ればいいじゃん
By making it a club, she can go home after playing at school.
There's no problem at all that way.
だったら全然問題ないよ
あっ でも服を汚すと
また叔母さんに…
But if she gets her clothes dirty, she won't hear the end of it...
そしたら アウトドアじゃなくて
インドア中心にすればいいわけよ
Then we don't go outside, but concentrate on indoor activities.
インドアってことは教室で？
Indoor?
You mean in the classroom?
This might come as a surprise, but I love games.
おじさん こう見えても
ゲームが大好きでね
I've collected quite a bit of games, even valuable ones from overseas.
海外の貴重な物とか
結構 集めてたりするんだよ
Do you think Satoko can play those?
それ 沙都子にも遊べるかな？
Of course!
もちろん
それにルールなんてね―
Besides, if we don't know the rules, we'll just make some up on the spot!
分かんなかったら
その場で作っちゃえばいいんだよ
Okay?
ねっ！
（悟史）うん　分かった
Okay.
あっ あとさ 魅音
相談があるんだけど…
Another thing, Mion...
I want to talk to you about something.
んっ？　何？
About what?
I'm looking for a part-time job.
僕 アルバイトを探してるんだ
I was thinking about getting Satoko a wonderful birthday present to cheer her up.
沙都子を元気づけるのに―
誕生日に
すてきなプレゼントをしたら
喜ぶかなって思って
I figured it might make her happy.
Those pills you got from the doctor.
（レナの母）
お医者さんにもらった薬―
Keep taking them until the end, even if you've already recovered.
症状が回復しても
最後まで飲みきりなさい
Understand, Reina?
分かった？　礼奈(れいな)
You're sure?
（レナの母）いいのね？
本当に一緒に来ないのね？
You really won't come with me?
I see.
そう
ハア… ハア…
（レナ）ひっ！
（羽入(はにゅう)）ごめんなさい
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
（羽入）
ごめんなさい ごめんなさい
Oyashiro-sama...
（レナ）オヤシロさま…
Excuse me!
（レナ）ごめんください
（女性）
はいはいはい　あれっ どちら様？
Coming.
Oh, who might you be?
Umm...
（レナ）
あの 私 お隣に引っ越してきました
竜宮(りゅうぐう)と申します
My name is Ryuuguu. We recently moved in next door.
I came to say hello.
引っ越しのごあいさつに
お伺いしました
Ryuuguu-san, Ryuuguu-san...
竜宮さん 竜宮さん…
ああ もしかして礼奈ちゃんかい？
Could you be Reina-chan?
アハハッ 覚えててくれたんですか
So you remembered?
I see, I see.
そうかいそうかい 戻ってきたかい
やっぱり 都会よか―
So you returned.
It really is much more comfortable here than in the city, right, Reina-chan?
村のほうが落ち着くんねえなあ
礼奈ちゃん
（レナ）はい
Yes...
あ… あの 私の名前
礼奈じゃなくてレナです
Umm...
My name is Rena, not Reina.
Huh?
あれ？　そうだっけ
（レナ）はい レナです
Really?
Yes.
It's Rena.
アハハッ ごめん ごめん
レナちゃんだね
Sorry about that. Rena-chan it is.
Yes!
はい
それじゃあ 失礼します
（女性）ご苦労様
See you later!
Thanks for visiting!
（レナ）
そう　私は もう礼奈じゃない
Right.
I am not Reina anymore.
I will restart my life under a new name.
新しい名前で新しい生活をやり直す
My name is...
私の名前は…
（悟史）ハア… んっ！
ああ！　ハッ ああ レナか
It's you, Rena.
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
（悟史）えっ？
具合悪そうだから
You don't look too good.
Thanks for your concern.
ありがとう　大丈夫だよ
But I'm fine.
Are you worrying about Satoko-chan?
沙都子ちゃんのことで心配事？
No, it's not that...
いや そういうわけじゃないんだ
I only just tranferred so I might not be of much help...
レナは転校してきたばかりだから
頼りないかもしれないけど―
話を聞くことくらいはできるからね
...but I can at least listen to you.
（悟史）足音がついてくるんだ
（レナ）えっ？
Footsteps are following me around.
Tap, tap... Step, step...
I know about that.
（レナ）私 知ってる
（悟史）えっ？
その足音 知ってる
I know about those footsteps.
I see...
（入江(いりえ)）そうですか
You're one of our Hinamizawa Fighters' promising players, after all.
悟史君は我が雛見沢(ひなみざわ)ファイターズの
頼もしい選手ですからね
I'll keep your position free.
籍は ちゃんと空けておきますから
No...
いえ 当分は
戻ってこられないと思うので―
I probably won't be able to come back for a while.
I think it's best for me to just resign...
一度 退部にしてもらったほうが
いいと思いまして
（入江）何かあったんですか？
Did something happen?
Actually, I'm going to start working.
実は僕 アルバイトを始めるんです
それで…
So...
Work?
アルバイトですか
Yes.
はい
もうすぐ沙都子の誕生日なんです
Satoko's birthday is just around the corner.
沙都子が欲しがっている
ぬいぐるみがあるので―
There's this teddy bear that she wanted to have...
I was thinking of giving it to her as a present.
それを プレゼントしてやりたいと
思いまして
Is that so.
そうですか　悟史君は
本当に妹思いのお兄さんですね
You really are a caring brother.
喜んでくれると うれしいです
I hope she'll be happy with it.
Understood.
分かりました　そういうことなら
In that case...
（悟史）それと監督
バット 持ち帰ってもいいですか？
Oh, and Manager...
...could I take my bat back home with me?
バットですか？
Your bat?
Well...
その… １人で―
I think I'll still have some time to practice swinging by myself...
素振りの練習をするくらいの
時間は取れると思うので
I see.
そうですか
ぜひ持っていってください
Feel free to take it with you.
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
それじゃ また
See you later.
（熊谷(くまがい)）
やっぱり 起こっちまったんですね
Looks like it happened again after all.
Oyashiro-sama's curse.
（熊谷）オヤシロさまの祟(たた)り
（大石(おおいし)）
んっ 敵は必ず取ってやりますよ
おやっさん
I will definitely avenge you, old man.
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni
Kai
アハハッ 大きいですねえ
It's huge!
You definitely can't carry this on a bike.
確かに これでは
自転車じゃ運べませんね
Sorry to trouble you.
すみません
（入江）しかし 高かったでしょ
But it must've been expensive.
Yeah, sort of...
ええ まあ
What's wrong?
どうしましたか？
具合でも悪いんですか？
Are you not feeling well?
I'm fine.
いえ ただの風邪だと思います
I think I just have a cold.
That isn't good.
それは よくありませんね
診療所で診てあげましょう
I'll give you a check-up at the clinic.
Thank you.
ありがとうございます　ハア
Aunt is no longer here.
もう 叔母さんはいない
There's no one to torment Satoko anymore, right?
これで 沙都子をいじめる人は
いないんですよね？
That's right.
そうですね　もう 沙都子ちゃんを
いじめる人はいません
There is no longer anyone to torment Satoko-chan.
You can live out a peaceful life from now on.
だから これからは
ゆっくりと過ごしていいんですよ
Aunt really isn't here anymore, is she?
本当に
叔母さんは いないんですよね？
んっ？
（悟史）死んだんですもんね？
After all, she's dead, right?
Yes.
はい 確かに死にました
検視には私も立ち会っていますから
She definitely died.
I was present during the autopsy.
You really made absolutely sure she was dead, right?
本当に 本当に叔母さんが
死んでるのを確認したんですよね？
Yes.
はい 間違いなく
There's no doubt about it.
Then...
じゃあ たまに通り過ぎる―
...even if people who look exactly like Aunt pass by...
叔母さんに
そっくりな人がいても―
それは
叔母さんじゃないんですよね？
...those people aren't actually her, right!?
Right...
Then...
（悟史）じゃあ じゃあ あの
（ブレーキ音）
Then!
That...
That person...!
あの人は!?
She looks a lot like her...
あれもよく似てるけど
叔母さんじゃないんですよね？
...but she isn't my aunt, right!?
Look, that person too!
ほら あの人も！
Even though she's her spitting image...
あんなにそっくりでも
叔母さんじゃないんですか!?
...she really isn't my aunt!?
After all...
だって 僕を見ましたよ！
...I saw it!
Please calm down, Satoshi-kun.
落ち着いてください 悟史君
叔母さんは本当に死にました
Your aunt really is dead.
So no matter how much they resemble her, they aren't your aunt.
だから どんなに似ていても
それは叔母さんではありません
They look like her...
似てる 似てる いや違う
本当に叔母さんなんだ
They look like her!
No!
They don't just look like her!
It really is Aunt.
Aunt is still...
叔母さんはまだ まだ…
Still...
Even though I killed her!
あんなに殺したのに！
あんなに殴ったのに！
I battered her up so bad!
Why...
なんで… なんで！
Why!
ハアハア
（入江）悟史君
Satoshi-kun...
Manager...
監督 これってやっぱり―
Is this...
...Oyashiro-sama's curse?
オヤシロさまの
祟りなんでしょうか？
There is no such thing as a curse!
祟りなんてありません
どうか気を強く持ってください
Try to stay focused!
Satoko...
沙都子… ごめん
I'm sorry...
In truth...
本当は… 本当は僕
ぬいぐるみを買う直前まで―
In truth, until right before I bought the teddy bear...
...I was planning on using the money to run somewhere far away.
そのお金でどこか遠くに
逃げてしまおうって思ってたんだ
That's why...
だから そんな僕を
オヤシロさまは許さなかったんだ
...Oyashiro-sama didn't want to let me go unpunished.
I'm a failure of an older brother.
僕は兄失格なんだ　僕は 僕は…
I... I...
Try not to talk too much.
無理にしゃべらなくていいですよ
すぐに診療所に着きますからね
We're almost at the clinic.
ハアハア 僕の血の中にも
うじ虫が湧いてるのかな
I wonder if there are maggots crawling around in my blood as well...
うう かゆい！
（入江）かかないで！
It itches!
Don't scratch!
You mustn't scratch your throat!
のどをかいてはいけません！
（悟史）ううっ
[Irie Clinic]
（悟史）ハア…
Manager...
監督… 助けて…
Help me...
Hurry up!
（職員）さあ 早く
（鷹野(たかの)）あらあら
Oh my.
What is up with this ruckus?
（鷹野）騒がしいと思ったら
これは何事ですの？
It seems Satoshi-kun has acutely fallen to the symptoms.
悟史君が急性発症したようです
Considering his daily stress...
彼の日頃のストレスを考えれば―
...it was to be expected it would happen one day.
いつ発症しても
おかしくなかったんでしょう
No...
いや ぬいぐるみを買うまで
自制心で―
He must have been suppressing it through sheer willpower until he was able to buy this teddy bear.
それをずっと抑え続けてきたに
違いありません
It seems that whenever Watanagashi arrives, we are getting our hands on a live sample...
なんだか綿流しの時期になると
生きた検体が手に入りますわねえ
んっ？
（鷹野）ンフッ これも―
Could this also be thanks to Oyashiro-sama's curse?
オヤシロさまの祟りの
おかげなのかしら
ンフッ ンフフッ
This is a nice village.
（梨花）ここは いい村なのですよ
（梨花）きっと都会には
なかったものがあるのです
I'm sure there are things here that you didn't have in the city.
I suppose so.
（伊知郎）
そうだね　私もそんな気がするよ
I feel that way as well.
I have a feeling you will bring something from the city that can't be found here.
この村にないものを―
きっと都会のあなたが
持ってきてくれる気がするのです
Do you really think we have such a thing?
そんなもの 私たちにあるのかなあ
You definitely have.
ありますのですよ　あうあう
We have been living in the village like this for a long time.
僕たちは
この村でずーっとこうしています
That's why nothing happened, and nothing changed.
だから 何も起きないし
何も変えられない
Isn't the fact that nothing changes a quality of this village?
（伊知郎）何も変わらないのが
この村のいいとこじゃないのかい？
Did you not come to this village because you sought change?
何かを変えたいと思ったから
この村に来たのじゃないのですか？
That's certainly true.
確かにそうだね
We wish to welcome new people here as well.
（梨花）
僕たちも新しい人を迎えたい
それは例えるなら―
To give an analogy...
水の流れ出ぬ沼の堤を
破るようなもの
...it is like breaking open an embankment that prevents stale water from draining out of a marsh.
Water purifies if it is allowed to stream.
水は出入りがあるからこそ
清水となる
A lake without currents is but a dank marsh.
流れを得ぬ湖は沼にすぎない
We have been waiting for you to move here...
（梨花）引っ越してくるのを
待っていますのですよ　前原(まえばら)
...Maebara.
ああ　えっ なんで名前を？
How do you know my name?
（不動産の社員）
ハア ああ いたいた
There you are!
お客さん
こんな遠くまで来ちゃダメですよ
Sir!
Please don't wander off so far!
ハアハアハア
（伊知郎）ああ すみません
Sorry.
It's almost time. Let's go.
そろそろ時間ですから行きましょう
Okay.
（伊知郎）はい
（不動産の社員）ハアハア
Huh?
あれ？　おじさん お久しぶりです
Uncle!
Long time no see!
おお 魅音ちゃん 今 帰りかい？
おじさんは今から送迎だよ
Ah, Mion-chan!
Did you just come home?
I was just about to go pick up some people.
ああ 不動産屋さんのお仕事？
どんな感じですか？
For your real estate business, right?
How's that going?
I'm surprised by how many people from the city showed interest!
都会の人が 案外
興味を持ってくれたから―
びっくりだわ
Oh boy.
やれやれ　物好きなことで
Curiosity seekers, huh?
We had one customer who even wanted to move here, instead of wanting a vacation home.
（社員）
一軒 別荘じゃなくて 引っ越しで
検討されてるお宅があってね
へえ そりゃすごいや！
You're kidding!
I'm off.
Hinamizawa Lot-for-sale Tour_________
Can I ask you something?
ねえ 聞いていい？
Why did you decide to put lots for sale, even though you hate outsiders?
よそ者嫌いの婆っちゃがさ―
どうして わざわざ
分譲地なんかにしたの？
I do hate outsiders, especially those from the city.
（お魎(りょう)）
あたしゃ よそもんなんか嫌いだし
都会もんも大嫌いだ
However, this is necessary for the village.
だが 村には必要なんよ
空気の入れ替えみたいなもんさなあ
It's like refreshing the air.
Refreshing the air?
空気の入れ替え？
Rena-chan of the Ryuuguus moved here from outside and became your friend, right?
外から竜宮のレナちゃんが
引っ越してきて―
友達になってくれたんだろが
You said you were happy to have made a friend close to your age.
“近い年の友達ができて
うれしい”言うとったがな
Yeah.
It's great to be able to unexpectedly make friends.
予期せぬ友達が
突然できるのはいいね　ンフッ
Before Rena-chan came, you used to complain about how boring it was at school all the time.
“学校が退屈だ 退屈だ”
言うとったんね
よう覚えとる　ンフフッ
I remember well.
Are you saying this was a positive effect of having people move in?
それが“外から
引っ越してくることによる効果だ”
って言いたいわけ？
No matter how cold the winter, some ventilation is neccesary every now and then.
どんな寒い冬場かて
たまには換気をせんとな
Otherwise, all kinds of polluted air will pile up until you end up suffocating.
囲炉裏の悪い空気がたまって
窒息しちまう
Sometimes, you have to accept the chilly winds and open up the windows.
寒くてしんどいのは承知で
窓をガラリと開けることもあるんよ
So a person moving in from outside is fresh air for the village?
外から人を迎えることが
村の換気になるってこと？
Exactly.
ああ　そして
きれいな空気を入れて―
Fresh air comes in, and stale air like us will have to be driven out.
あたしらみたいな悪い空気は
とっとと追い出されるべきなんよ
Isn't that a bit too much to expect from the person moving in?
引っ越してくる人に そこまでを
期待しちゃうのは気の毒じゃない？
No matter who moves in, I'm sure the village will change.
誰が引っ越してきても
きっと村は変わる
Though I would hope for it to be an energetic young one...
願わくば それが元気な若者で―
...reliable enough for us old timers to be able to leave the village in his care without worries.
わしら年寄り連中が
安心して村を任せられるくらい―
大暴れしてくれよると
うれしいんだが
I'll be glad if he manages to cause a good stir here.
ふうん
Mion.
（お魎）魅音
（魅音）ん？
On the day Satoshi of the Houjous disappeared...
お前 北条(ほうじょう)の悟史が消えた日
あたしに詰め寄ったろが
...you confronted me.
ああ そんなこともしたね　アハハ
I guess I did...
You know...
あたしゃなあ
あれで目が覚めたんよ
...that opened up my eyes.
I figured the conflict with the Houjou family would resolve itself with time after the old guard died out.
北条家が
どうのこうのいう問題は―
“年寄りどもが死ねば―”
“時間が解決してくれる”
なんてんじゃあかんね
But we shouldn't wait for that. It needs to be resolved sooner than that.
そんなの待たず
早(はよ)う解決せなあかん
You can't do it yourself...
自分には それができないから
よそ者にそれを託すってこと？
...so you're leaving the task up to an outsider?
That is the best I can do.
それが あたしにできる
精いっぱいだんね　うん
So you're relying on salvation by others?
他力本願の極みだね
The new wind will be of your generation.
（お魎）新しい風は
魅音 お前らの世代になる
外の風を迎え入れたれな
Accept the wind from outside.
Then mingle in as the wind from the inside...
そして お前は
内からの風となって混じり合い―
村のよどみを吹き飛ばしてくれ
...and help blow out the stagnation from the village.
If that is my job as the future family head...
それが次期頭首の仕事だってんなら
I'm counting on you, Mion.
（お魎）
頼むわ 魅音　あたしゃ老いたんね
I have grown old.
I can only do the thankless jobs anymore.
もう憎まれ役しかできん
Cast
Keiichi Maebara
Rena Ryuuguu
Mion Sonozaki
Rika Furude
Satoko Houjou
Hanyuu
Souichiro Hoshi
Mai Nakahara
Satsuki Yukino
Yukari Tamura
Mika Kanai
Yui Horie
anata no nakigara ni tsuchi wo kakeru
I cover your corpse with soil...
Cast
Kuraudo Ooishi
Katsuya Kumagai
Oryou
Kyousuke Irie
Miyo Takano
Chafuurin
Takuo Kawamura
Shizuka Okohira
Toshihiko Seki
Miki Itou
Cast
Satoshi Houjou
Principal Kaieda
Rumiko Chie
Rena's Mother
Ichirou Maebara
Housewife
Realtor
Yuu Kobayashi
Yousuke Akimoto
Fumiko Orikasa
Miki Suga
Yasunori Matsumoto
Eriko Matsushima
Satoshi Tsuruoka
sore ga kinjirareteita toshitemo
...even though that may have been forbidden.
junsui na manazashi no kairaku ni wa
There was a temptation you could not hide...
kakushikirenai yuuwaku ga atta
...in your pure, blissful eyes.
doushite tsumi ga aru no darou
Why does sin exist?
Ending Theme
"Taishou a"
(Target a)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition/
Arrangement
doushite batsu ga aru no darou
Why does punishment exist?
hone no saki wa amari ni mo shiroku
That blindingly white tip of the bone...
mugen ni tsuzuku yami wo sasotta
...invited the infinite darkness.
Scenario
Toshifumi Kawase
Storyboards
Episode Direction
Nobuhiro Takamoto
Yuuji Seki
nani mo kamo ga azayaka ni miete
I can see everything clearly now.
Animation Supervisors
Minefumi Harada
Hiromichi Mizukawa
Akiko Nakano
sugu ni kieteshimau
It will soon vanish.
Animation Production
Studio Deen
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
© 2007 Ryukishi07/Hinamizawa Three Great Houses
Is this the school?
（圭一(けいいち)）これが学校なのかよ
すっげえな　さすが田舎だぜ
Whoa.
This really is the countryside.
Keiichi.
（伊知郎）圭一
そんなこと言っちゃダメだぞ
Don't say that.
To the people here, it's a wonderful school.
ここの人にとっては
立派な学校なんだからな
（海江田(かいえだ)）
アハハッ　まあ 確かに―
Well, sure enough.
We're just a branch school who borrowed a building from the Forestry Preserve.
我が校は 営林署の敷地を
お借りしてできた分校ですからのう
I'm sure the ways of this school will be very different from what you're used to.
（知恵(ちえ)）前原君が
今まで通われてた学校とは―
いろいろルールが違うと思いますが
大丈夫ですか？
Are you ready for that?
（圭一）あっ はい
Yes, Ma'am.
Dad.
父さん 俺 気に入ったよ
I like it here.
I prefer this school over the one in the city.
街の学校より
こっちの学校のほうがいいや
Looks like our school will become lively again.
（海江田）
これでまた
我が校もにぎやかになりますな
アハハッ
If he misbehaves, don't hesitate to give him hell!
悪さをした時は
ガツンと言ってやってください
So you've finally moved here.
ようやく引っ越してきたのです
僕らは待ち疲れたのですよ
We were getting tired of waiting.
あうあう
これでまた変わってくるのです
Things are going to change again now.
After all, Keiichi is our trump card who taught us how to make a miracle happen.
だって 圭一は僕たちに―
奇跡の起こし方を教えてくれる
切り札なのですから
But Keiichi's miracles often collapse at important times.
でも 圭一が起こす奇跡は―
肝心なところで
よく こけやがりますです
あうあうあうあう　圭一が
悪いわけではありませんのです
Keiichi isn't at fault for that!
You are to blame for that.
全部 羽入が悪いのです
お前のせいなのです
It's your fault.
圭一に謝れなのです
Apologize to Keiichi.
So far, we have only assembled the usual pieces on the game board.
私たちは ゲーム盤の上に―
これまでと同じ駒しか
まだ並べていない
We are missing the piece holding the power we came short up until now.
今まで足りなかった
強い力を持ち―
The piece with the power to smash Takano's will.
鷹野の意志を
打ち砕いてくれる強さを持った駒
That is you.
それはあなた
あっ
（梨花）羽入
Hanyuu.
It's you.
あなたなのよ
Come, let us begin.
さあ 始めましょう
I have lived a hundred years for this day.
この日のために
100年もの時間をかけたんだから
（羽入）
“教えて 黒梨花”コーナー！
"Tell me, Dark Rika" corner!
相談者は雛見沢村の
北条鉄平(てっぺい)さんなのです
Our caller is Mr. Teppei Houjou from Hinamizawa.
（梨花）またこいつ？
This guy again?
（羽入）以前から
疑問に思っていたことですが―
"This has puzzled me for some time...
羽入さんは 一体何者でしょうか？
What on earth is Hanyuu?
誰かが言っているように―
Is she really an alien who came from the M37 star cluster like someone says?
Ｍ37星雲から来た
宇宙人なのでしょうか？
だとしたら
胸とか腕とかおでこから―
And if so, can she shoot laser beams from her chest, her arms or her forehead?
ビーム光線出しちゃったり
するんでしょうか？
お答えください
Please answer!"
（梨花）
自分のことくらい自分で答えなさい
Answer questions about yourself, yourself.
ピコーン ピコーン ピコー…
あうう！
Blink.
Blink, blink.
次回　祭囃し編 其の六
「幕開け」
Next time, the Festival Accompanying Chapter, Part Six.
"Beginning."
バビューン！
（梨花）逃げたわね
So you ran away.
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai
Next time
Festival Accompanying Chapter
Part Six
Beginning